大家好，我是安德魯·梅恩。
Hello, I'm Andrew Mayne
歡迎收聽《開眼》播客。
and this is the Opening Eye podcast.
今天我們要來聊聊 ChatGPT 與教育。
Today, we're going to talk about chat GPT and education.
它會讓人變笨嗎？
Does it cause brain rot?
ChatGPT 只是拿來作弊的工具嗎？
Is chat GPT just a tool for cheating?
我們將邀請莉亞·貝爾斯基來聊聊，
We're going to speak with Leah Belsky,
她是《開眼》的教育主管，
head of education at Opening Eye
還有幾位經常使用的學生。
and a couple of students who are active users.
現在，ChatGPT 已經是全球最大的學習平台。
Chat GPT at this point is now the world's largest learning platform.
它能幫你排除雜訊，
It allows you to kind of cut through the noise
讓你專注做自己真正喜歡的事。
and do things that you actually enjoy.
ChatGPT 將為這位女孩打開世界的大門，
Chat GPT is going to unlock the world for this girl
我也不用再像以前那樣擔心了。
and I was not going to have to be worried in the same way.
說到學習和探索新想法，
When it comes to learning and exploring ideas
我常常會問 ChatGPT 這些問題。
I ask chat GPT a lot of those questions.
跟我聊聊你加入 OpenAI 的經歷吧。
Tell me about your journey to Opening Eye.
你知道嗎，
You know,
我認為 OpenAI 最終關乎使命，也關乎這裡的人。
I think ultimately Open AI is about a mission and about its people.
所以我至少可以跟你分享我的故事。
And so I'll tell you at least my story.
我在教育領域耕耘了十五年後，來到了 OpenAI，
So I came to Open AI after spending 15 years in the education space,
一開始在世界銀行，後來加入 Coursera，
starting at the World Bank and then at Coursera
一直專注於讓全球都能獲得教育的使命。
focused on this mission of making education accessible to the world.
當我接下這份工作時，我們的營運長 Brad，
And when I and I took on this job, Brad, our COO
他把我帶進辦公室，你知道的，
he brought he brought me into the office and, you know
我當時在想，究竟
I was wondering what what the exact
OpenAI 在教育領域的重點會是什麼。
focus of education at Open AI would be.
然後他請我坐下，對我說，Leah，你知道嗎，
And and he sat me down and he said, Leah, you know
我希望你去追尋那個大膽的目標。
I want you to go after the moonshot.
我們每個人都有這個夢想，
We all have this dream
那就是我們能提升人類的潛能。
that that I could improve human potential
它能成為一位有效的家教
that it could be an effective tutor
並且能陪伴人們一生。
and a companion for people throughout their lives.
追逐那個夢想，並確保
Go after that dream and make sure
當我們打造出那個產品時
that once we build that product
全世界每個人都能擁有它。
everyone in the world can have it.
這一直是我們的指引方向。
And that's really been the North Star.
我覺得這很有意義，你知道嗎，
And I thought that was meaningful, you know,
從市場推廣負責人的角度來看，
from the head of go to market,
甚至連營收主管也說，
the head of revenue to say,
追求最具變革性的遠大目標，
go after the biggest transformative moonshot so
讓最高的期望
that the highest and hopes
以及我們對 AI 和教育的夢想都能實現。
and dreams that we all have for AI and education can be realized.
這真的很鼓舞人心，也充滿希望，
That's pretty inspiring and hopeful
希望能讓這項技術盡可能普及的想法。
the idea of trying to make this widespread as possible.
你怎麼看待這對全球的影響呢？
How do you see basically, you know, global impact?
我們要怎麼做，你知道的，
How are we going to, you know
才能看到這件事在全世界產生的影響？
see the effects of this around the world?
嗯，
Well,
首先要說的是，像ChatGPT這樣的平台現在
first thing to say is like Chachapiti at
已經成為全球最大的學習平台。
this point is now the world's largest learning platform.
學習是最主要的用途之一，
Learning is one of the top use
目前平台上有六億名用戶。
cases on the platform at 600 million users.
這代表它已經成為全球學習的首選平台。
That means it is the world's learning destination.
而且這也代表著在正規教育體系之外的學習。
And that means learning outside of the educational system.
我真的認為ChatGPT是學習的新前沿。
I really see Chachapiti as a new frontier for learning.
但我們也發現老師是主要的
But we also see that teachers are major
平台使用者之一，
adopters of the of the of the platform
他們不僅用它來減輕
and they are using that both to get
自己工作的行政負擔，
rid of the administrative burden of their own work
也把它帶進了教室。
but also to to bring it to their classroom.
令人驚訝的是，全球對ChatGPT的需求如此之高。
What's been striking is to see the global demand for Chachapiti.
所以幾個星期前，
So a few weeks ago
我們推出了一個名為「OpenAI for Countries」的計畫，
we launched a program called Open AI for Countries
世界各地的政府部門都主動聯繫我們。
and we've had ministries all over the world reach out.
愛沙尼亞，這個國家，
Estonia, the country of Estonia
其實是最早聯絡我們的國家之一。
was actually one of the first countries that reached out.
愛沙尼亞會這麼做很合理。
Estonia makes sense.
他們在世界上名列前茅。
They are that they are the top of the world.
他們的PISA成績是全球頂尖之一。
They have some of the best PISA scores.
他們擁有非常優秀的教育體系。
They have an amazing educational system.
但他們是第一個意識到：「哇，
But they were the first to realize, wow
這是讓學生更上一層樓的機會，
this is an opportunity to push students even further
也能進一步賦能我們的教師。」
and to empower our teachers even further.
在愛沙尼亞之後，陸續有越來越多國家加入。
And after Estonia, it's been one country after another.
有趣的是，
And what's interesting is
當各國來找我們的時候，
that when the countries come to us,
你知道，他們會來找我們，
you know, they're coming to us
是因為他們想要在教育體系中導入人工智慧，
because they want to deploy AI
把它作為教育系統的核心基礎建設。
as core infrastructure through their education system.
但他們同時也來找我們，
But they're also coming to us
因為他們正感受到經濟轉型帶來的衝擊。
because they're feeling like the impact of an economic transition.
他們也意識到，如果他們要
And they're realizing that if they are
發展一個以人工智慧為核心的經濟，
going to be developing an AI powered economy
他們就必須培養出
they need to they need to graduate
懂得如何運用人工智慧的勞動力。
a workforce that learns how to use AI.
所以這不只是開設新的人工智慧課程，
And so it's not just about creating new AI courses.
他們還必須確保
They need to make sure
每一位從中學畢業的學生
that every student who leaves their secondary school
都曾在課堂上實際使用過人工智慧。
system has used AI as part of their class.
因此，這些國家同時聚焦於兩個重點。
And so it's that it's that dual focus of these countries.
他們希望在經濟上保持競爭力。
They're looking to be economically competitive.
他們想培養具備 AI 能力的勞動力。
They want to build an AI ready workforce.
他們希望能在新興的 AI 經濟中取得成功。
They want to be successful in a new AI powered economy.
同時也希望提升教育體系。
And they want to improve their education system.
你從教育夥伴和機構那邊聽到什麼反饋？
What are you hearing from educational partners and institutions?
我們收到幾個方面的回應。
So we're hearing a couple of things.
我認為那些已經投入資源的人
I think those that have made the investment
對於他們所取得的成就感到自豪，
feel a certain pride that they have
像是在校園內實現了 AI 的平等使用。
equalized access to AI on their campuses.
他們真的相信 AI
They are they really believe that AI
應該成為校園的核心基礎設施，
should be core infrastructure for the campus
並且應該對所有人開放。
and that it should be open to everyone.
他們也意識到，
They're conscious that, you know
在許多校園導入 AI 之前，
before introducing AI in many campus
你會遇到這樣的情況
you'll find a situation
那些沒有申請經濟補助的人
where those who are not on financial aid
會自費購買最新的模型使用權限。
will be buying access to the latest models.
而缺乏資源的人則無法這麼做。
And those who don't have access to resources will not.
因此，推動平等取得資源是一件值得自豪的事。
So there's a there's a pride in and driving equal access.
我認為這些機構也非常渴望彼此交流合作
I think their institutions are also hungry to engage with each other
並且合作了解目前最受歡迎的五種
and collaborate and understand what are the top five
或十種教師運用這項技術的方式
or ten ways in which faculty are using the tech
並將其應用在教學現場。
and bringing it into the classroom.
不過，我們也收到另一種回饋，指出
The other type of feedback that we're getting, though, is that
學生對於使用學校提供的某些AI工具感到猶豫。
students are hesitant to use some of the school provided AI.
除非大學特別強調告訴學生們
And unless universities make a big point of telling students
我們並不會監控這些工具的使用情形
that we're not monitoring this tech
我們也不會查看你們的對話內容。
we're not looking at your conversations.
否則學生會對使用這些工具感到遲疑。
Students are hesitant to adopt it.
你知道嗎，
You know,
令人注意的是，現在的大學生這一代
what's striking is that the generation of students that is
其實就是所謂的疫情世代，
in universities right now is the covid generation,
對不對？
right?
他們習慣於第一次接觸科技時，
They are used to having some of their first experiences
就是透過 Zoom、全球教室這些方式，
with tech be about like Zoom and global classroom and having
老師不是在大聲斥責，就是在監控他們，
teachers screaming at them or monitoring
還會說他們沒寫作業，
and telling them they're not doing that homework
而他們卻只能在家裡快要抓狂。
while they're all sitting at home going crazy.
所以他們對教育科技會感到猶豫。
And so they're hesitant about educational technology.
而大學也開始意識到，如果
And universities are realizing that if
他們想要和學生有更多互動，
they want to engage with students
並且用 ChatGPT 幫助學生用新方式學習，
and help students learn in new ways with chat GPT
就必須真正建立起和學生的信任。
they need to build an actual trust with students.
對啊，我只是覺得很挫折，
Yeah, I just like I was frustrated
因為那些 AI 偵測器真的很不準。
because like the AI detectors were terrible.
就像有些 AI 偵測工具一樣。
Like there are these AI detect like one.
我可以教別人怎麼寫出會被判定為 AI 生成的文字，
I could show somebody how to write text that would be flagged as AI
也可以教他們怎麼下提示詞來避開偵測。
and also how to prompt a thing to avoid it.
這就造成了這種，你知道的，
And that just created this, you know
一開始就產生的關係。
relationship that started off.
如果你用這種爛工具，你懂的，
If you're using a bad tool like that, you know
你可能會把一兩個沒作弊的學生誤判成作弊。
you take one or two students who didn't cheat and told their cheaters.
就是這樣。
That's just.
對啊。
Yeah.
而且在很多學校裡，
And in many institutions
我覺得我們一開始就走錯方向了。
I would say we got off onto the wrong foot.
沒錯。
Yeah.
在教室裡使用 AI，與其試著明確說清楚，
With AI in the classroom, instead of trying to be explicit
並訂立明確的規範，
and establish clear policies on
學生什麼時候該用科技，什麼時候不該用
when students should use the tech and when they shouldn't
老師們一開始有點避開這件事。
teachers sort of hid from it.
我們一開始只是在管控它的使用，而不是靜下心來
We started with policing its use rather than actually sitting there
思考我們究竟該怎麼
and figuring out how do we actually
重新設計我們評量學生的方式
want to redesign the way we assess students
還有我們布置作業的方式。
and the way we assign homework.
但我覺得我們正在進步。
But I think we're moving.
我們已經跨過那個階段了。
We're moving beyond that point.
是啊，這讓我很受鼓舞。
Yeah, I've been encouraged.
我記得我在這裡的時候，我們看到
And we saw I remember when I was here
有一個學校系統當時有點
we had one school system that was like kind
反射性地說要禁止它。
of a knee jerk reaction said we're banning it.
結果過了幾個月，
And it was like a few months later
裡面有不少老師開始說，欸，不對，
they had enough teachers within there going, hey, no
這其實是個很棒的工具。
this is a really good tool.
我們知道該怎麼教這個。
We know how to teach to this.
他們就說，好啊，
And they said, OK
我們現在要改變這個做法。
we're going to reverse that now.
事情就是這樣，這真的很
And that was it was it was very
很高興看到充滿熱情的老師們接受這個，並說，好啊，
good to see energized teachers embrace this and say, OK
因為他們希望學生能理解，
in wanting their students to understand
他們知道這會成為未來的一部分。
they knew this was going to be part of the future.
現在有了學習模式。
Well, now there's study mode.
你可以稍微聊聊這個嗎？
Could you talk a little about that?
學習模式是我們剛推出的功能，
So study mode is a product we just launched
目的是要真正提升學習成效，
and it is intended to take really improve learning
並將 ChatGPT 從只專注於提供答案的體驗，
and chat GPT and take it from an experience that is just focused
轉變為真正引導學生找到答案。
on giving answers to really guiding a student to get to the answers.
所以在學習模式下，
So study in study mode.
ChatGPT 會用蘇格拉底式提問來回答。
Chachapati answers socratically.
它會根據你的學習程度，量身打造回應。
It personalizes responses to sort of the level of your learning.
它能掌握你正在學習的脈絡。
It understands the context of what you're learning.
它會提出很有深度的追問。
It asks great follow up questions.
它會詢問你是否想針對這個主題進行測驗。
It asks if you want to have a quiz on the topic.
它會鼓勵你更深入探索。
It encourages you to to go deeper.
而最終，
And ultimately,
這是邁向真正學習的第一步，
this is this is a first step to really leaning
讓 ChatGPT 成為你專屬家教的概念。
into this idea of of Chachapati as a as a tutor.
那這個想法是怎麼產生的？
So how did this come about?
有跟教育工作者和家長討論過這件事嗎？
Was there conversations with educators and parents about this?
其實學習模式是我們團隊去印度時誕生的，
So study mode actually came out of a trip that our team took in India,
當時他們有一些發現，
where they had a few
他們意識到幾個重點。
where they realized a few things.
首先，他們發現像印度這樣的地方，
One, they realized that in a place like India
許多家庭花了很大一部分的
families were spending a huge percentage of their
每人平均花在家教和課後輔導上的收入。
per capita income on tutors and after school help.
他們也發現，年輕人有著強烈的意願
They also realized that there was just a tremendous will
和渴望想要更上一層樓。
and desire among young people to get to get to the next level.
所以，你知道的，
And so, you know
我們就這樣開始了這段旅程，
we began this journey of like
我們需要做什麼，才能讓ChatGPT
what would it take to actually get Chachapati
變成比現在更優秀的家教？
and turn Chachapati into an even better tutor than it already is?
所以我們一開始就，
And so we started by, you know
這也是我第一次參與打造AI產品的經驗。
and this was my first my first experience building like an AI product.
我們開始根據學習科學建立一套架構，
So we started actually building a schema informed by learning science
並且參考教學專家的建議，
and informed by pedagogical experts that said
ChatGPT應該如何回應？
how should Chachapati respond?
它不只是單純給你答案，
It's not just going to give answers
而是會真正協助你，
but it's going to actually help you.
讓你真的學會。
You'd learn.
接著我們與全球的專家合作，
And then we work with open with experts around the world to
蒐集我們所謂的黃金範例，
gather what we call golden examples
這些都是Chachapati理想回應的範例。
of how Chachapati would ideally respond.
語氣是否具有鼓勵性？
Is the tone encouraging?
是否能激發好奇心？
Does it encourage curiosity?
回應是否貼合學生的需求程度？
Does it cater a response to the level of a student's need?
透過這樣反覆的過程，
And through that process of sort of going back
來回調整並訓練模型，
and forth and training the model
學習模式就是這樣誕生的。
that's how study mode emerged.
我想說，
And I would say, you know
我們非常期待看到大家的回饋，
we're super excited to see the feedback
來自全球對這項產品的反應，
on this product out in the world
但這同時也只是個開始。
but it's also very much a beginning.
沒錯，這是一個起點。
Yeah, it's a starting point.
這就是起點。
It's a starting point.
你知道嗎，
You know,
其實我們現在才剛開始探索
we've we're really only in the early stages of pushing the way in
讓這個模型能以多種形式回應的可能性。
which the model can respond in multimodal ways.
你知道嗎，
You know,
有一天你可以想像請學習模式提供你
one day you could imagine asking study mode to give you
一些生物作業的範例來幫你解釋有機化學
samples of a sort of a biology assignment to explain organic chemistry
還會跳出互動圖表，或適時提醒你，
and to pop up interactive diagrams or to nudge you,
例如三週後提醒你。
you know, three weeks down the road.
你還記得你曾經跟我說過
You remember you told me
你想要在今年的有機化學考試拿高分。
that you wanted to ace this year's organic chemistry exam.
我們現在要不要再回來討論這個主題？
Can shall we dig back into the topic now?
它可以主動陪伴你，長時間支持你的學習。
It could be proactive and really sort of travel with you over time.
我覺得隨著時間過去，
And I think over time
我們希望學習模式能發展到那個程度。
the hope is to get study mode to that point.
那真的很棒。
That'd be great.
沒錯，我覺得這如果結合間隔重複會很有效。
Yeah, I see that combined with spaced repetition.
而且你可以擁有一個不只是很棒的工具，
And you could have just a really good tool that doesn't just
不僅幫助你通過考試，
help you pass the test
還能讓你長時間記住內容。
but help you remember it for a long time.
我覺得你剛剛提到了一個重點，
And I think you touched about something there
就是在某些家庭裡，
which is that in, you know, certain households
他們有能力請私人家教。
they can afford to have private tutors.
家教課程確實很棒。
Tutoring program's great.
我們討論的是一種
And we talk about kind
教育機會上的差異。
of the differences in educational opportunities.
同一所學校裡可能有一群孩子，
You can have a bunch of kids that go to the same school
但那些能讓孩子
but the parents that are able to have the kid
去上家教課的家長，
go to a tutor are going to be in a situation
孩子通常會有更高的成就機會。
where the child's going to have a higher chance of an outcome.
現在你把這個視為一種平衡機會的工具。
Now you see this as a leveler.
你看，我認為AI最先產生重大影響的地方
Look, I think the first place
就是人工智慧帶來巨大改變的領域
where AI is having a huge impact
在教育上，其實並不是在教室裡。
in education is not even in the classroom.
而是在課堂之外，
It's outside of the classroom
它讓每個人都能獲得類似成人協助的資源，實現機會平等。
where it's equalizing access to what's really like adult support.
世界上有許多學生
There are many students out in the world
無法接觸到優質的老師。
who don't have access to a quality teacher.
他們也沒有補習老師可協助。
They don't have access to tutors.
他們的父母也無法
They don't have access to parents who
抽空坐下來幫他們學習。
are going to sit down and help them.
但現在有了AI，
And now with AI
他們可以擁有一個會鼓勵他們的學習夥伴，
they can have this companion who can encourage them
能針對作業或寫作給予回饋，
who can give feedback on their homework, on their writing
也能協助他們解答難題。
who can help them answer tough questions.
我們成立了一個由ChatGPT學生用戶組成的實驗小組。
We formed a lab of student users of ChatGPT.
它叫做 ChatGPT Lab。
It's called ChatGPT Lab.
我想你會和幾位學生聊聊。
I think you're going to talk to a few of the students.
有一點讓我很有感觸，他們說使用
And one thing that really struck me is they said using
使用 AI 讓他們更有自信，
using AI gave them confidence
甚至到了這樣的程度，
and it got to the place
以前遇到困難或感到沮喪的時候。
where formerly they would feel stuck or they would feel discouraged.
其中一位學生分享了她在課堂上的經歷，
One of the students told the story of being in the classroom
她是一位資工系的學生。
as a computer science student.
而且好幾年來，
And for many years
她在資工課程裡常常卡關，
she would get stuck in her computer science courses
甚至一度想要放棄。
and she started to give up.
她看不懂課本內容。
She couldn't understand the textbooks.
但當她在課外用 ChatGPT 當家教時，
But when she used ChatGPT out of school as a tutor
她開始覺得，啊，
she started to feel like, oh
我可以主動發問。
I can ask questions.
我可以理解這一點。
I can understand this.
比如說，
Like,
我有信心，也許我真的能繼續努力向前。
I have confidence and maybe I can actually continue and move forward.
所以我覺得這同樣重要，你知道的，
And so I think it's as much, you know
如果你想想看，家教在世界上扮演什麼角色，
if you think about what tutors do in the world
他們會給你鼓勵。
they give you encouragement.
他們會讓你產生『我可以做到』的自信感，
They give you a sense of confidence that I can
讓你有動力，也能繼續往前走。
and I want and I can move forward.
然後，當然，
And then, of course
他們會用貼近情境、個人化的方式傳達內容。
they deliver the content in contextual and personal ways.
我認為 ChatGPT 也能做到這些事情。
I think ChatGPT can do all of these things.
那麼談到職場生產力時，
So when it comes to workforce productivity
那在個人層面上是怎麼發揮作用的？
how does that work on a personal scale?
你會給大家什麼建議？
What advice would you give to people?
所有最新的數據都顯示，那些員工——
So all the recent data shows that workers who
在職場中運用人工智慧的人，生產力顯著提升。
use AI in the workforce are incredibly more productive.
這在某些領域尤其明顯，
It's particularly true in fields
像是專業服務業和金融相關領域。
like professional services and financial students.
但其實，
But, you know, really
現在任何畢業離校的學生都必須要
any graduate who who leaves institution today needs to
懂得如何在日常生活中運用人工智慧。
know how to use AI in their daily life.
這不僅體現在
And that will come in both
他們求職時，
when they're applying for jobs
也包括剛開始新工作的時候。
as well as when they start start their new job.
因此，其中一個重要原因是
And so one of the big reasons
學校現在將人工智慧作為核心
why institutions are now deploying AI as core
基礎設施佈建在校園各處，是希望
infrastructure across campus is they want to make
學生畢業時能具備這些職場技能。
sure their students leave with those workforce skills.
數據顯示，有七成
The data shows that seven in 10
雇主更傾向聘用懂得人工智慧的人。
employers would rather hire someone with AI
技能甚至超越那些擁有
skills over someone who had up to
在特定職能領域有十年經驗的人。
10 years of experience in a given function.
我親眼見過這種情況。
I've seen that.
我經營一家公司，專門協助組建
I run a firm where I help put together
團隊，與企業合作或協助他們導入人工智慧。
teams to work with companies or trying to deploy AI.
而我們在尋找合作夥伴時最重視的
And the thing that we look for in
就是他們是否具備人工智慧相關技能。
people we work with is basically AI skills.
例如，有人花了六個月學習如何運用這些技術。
Somebody who spent six months learning how to use this stuff.
我其實不在意他們的LinkedIn
I don't really care what their LinkedIn
或他們的學經歷背景長什麼樣。
or actually their curriculum looked like.
我只想知道
I just want to know
你有實際在用嗎？
have you been using it?
你會操作嗎？
Can you use it?
你聽我說，
Look,
我認為另一種很重要的核心素養
I think the other sort of core literacy
現在變得重要的，就是程式設計。
that's going to become important now is coding.
你知道，曾經有一段時間，
You know, for a while it was, you know
有一陣子我們認為所有學生都必須學習程式設計。
there was a moment where we thought all students need to learn coding.
後來，我覺得大家開始把重點放在工程師身上。
And then I think there was a big focus on engineers.
但現在隨著無程式碼開發的興起，
But now with vibe coding
而且現在有各種讓寫程式變得更簡單的工具，
and now that there are all sorts of tools that make coding easier
我認為我們會進入一個新階段，
I think we're going to get to a place
每個學生不僅要學會一般操作人工智慧，
where every student should not only learn how to use AI generally
還要學會運用人工智慧來創作，
but they should learn to use AI to create,
像是生成圖片、開發應用程式、撰寫程式碼。
to create image, to create create applications, to to write code.
我認為基本的程式設計將會成為一種核心素養。
And I think sort of basic coding is going to become a core literacy.
這一點同樣非常重要。
That's going to be important as well.
是啊，我也常聽到有人說，
Yeah, I get I hear people go like
既然AI會幫你寫程式，為什麼還要學寫程式？
why learn to code because AI codes for you.
但其實，
And it's like, like
如果書裡全都是文字，那我們為什麼還要學閱讀？
why learn to read if books are full of text?
我當下心裡想，才不是這樣
I was like, like, no
這世界還是靠這些東西在運作。
the world still runs on these things.
我想，沒錯
And I think, yeah
這真的很有價值。
it's a very valuable.
你知道，我有個同事
You know, one of my colleagues, you know
他主要做很多金融相關的事情
he does a lot of financial stuff
他還會開發新的計算機
and he's creating new calculators
而且經常在做各種小工具。
and building the little tools for this all the time.
我則是自己做一些工具
I build stuff for myself
用來學習或其他用途。
for learning and whatever.
而且我本來就會寫程式
And, you know, I already knew how to code
但這讓一切變得更簡單。
but it just makes it so much easier.
而且了解程式碼的運作很有效率。
And knowing what the code does is effective.
對，完全同意。
Yeah, absolutely.
所以我的看法是
So I'm of the view
隨著寫程式變得越來越簡單，
that as coding becomes something that's easier,
理解程式碼的能力
the ability to understand code
撰寫和除錯程式碼的能力將會成為一項基本素養。
to create it and debug it is going to become a core literacy.
這一點會變得越來越重要。
That's going to become increasingly more important.
沒錯，我覺得這是很棒的建議。
Yeah, I think that's great advice.
我認為人們花越多時間嘗試使用這些工具，
I think just the more time people spend trying to use these tools,
嘗試各種不同的方式和這些工具。
trying different things, these tools.
我聽過一個很有效的方法，
And one of the things I've heard that works really
就是定期和其他人聚會，
well is just meeting on a regular basis with other people
不管是在職場上，比如每週一次，
whether it's at a workplace, you know, like have once a week
或每個月聚一次，
or once a month to get together
一起討論事情，或讓學生分享他們的學習心得。
and talk about stuff or students sharing what they've learned.
最近有一些聳動的新聞標題在討論
So there's been some sort of sensational headlines talking about
AI在教育領域可能會導致大腦退化。
how AI can cause brain rot when it comes to education.
我明白你的想法
Look, I hear you
這是我每天都會被問到的問題之一。
and it's one of these questions I get asked every day.
人工智慧終究只是一個工具。
AI is ultimately a tool.
而在教育領域，最重要的是這個工具如何被運用。
And what matters most in education space is how that tool is used.
學習本來就需要努力與掙扎。
Learning takes struggle.
需要主動處理資訊。
It takes working with information.
還要消化這些資訊。
It takes processing it.
如果學生把人工智慧當成答案產生器來用，
If students use AI as an answer machine
他們就學不到東西。
they're not going to learn.
我想這就是大家所擔心的。
And so I think that's what people are are worried about.
所以我們的任務之一，就是協助學生
And so part of our journey here is really to help students
以及教育者善用人工智慧，來拓展批判性思維，
and educators use AI in ways that will expand critical thinking
並激發創造力。
that will expand creativity.
你不用去讀艱澀的研究報告也知道，
And you don't need to read complex studies to know
人工智慧的使用方式會帶來正面或負面的影響。
that AI used in certain ways is positive or negative.
我會想到我女兒，對吧？
I think of my daughter, right?
她現在正在學長除法。
She's learning long division right now.
這需要一點掙扎。
It takes a certain amount of struggle.
有時還會掉幾滴眼淚。
There's some tears involved.
如果我把計算機交給她，然後說，
If I were to hand her a calculator and said,
不要自己算除法題，
don't do the division problem
直接丟給 AI 算，
just put it into into AI
你就會學會長除法。
you're going to learn long division.
她其實學不會。
She wouldn't.
但同時，你知道，
But at the same time, you know
等她以後學更高階的數學時，
down the road as she's learning advanced math
我預期到時候我可以給她那台計算機，
I anticipate I can give her that calculator
她就能用它來算數學，
and she'll be able to you do math
而且能做到比原本更高層次。
at a higher level than she otherwise would.
AI 的使用方式也是一樣的道理。
AI uses is no different.
它必須以能夠促進回饋的方式來使用
It needs to be used in a way that drives feedback
讓人們能夠獲得個人化的輔導
that gives people personal tutoring
幫助你用各種不同的方式提問和回答問題。
that helps you ask and answer questions and in different ways.
這就是我們推動學習進步的方法。
That's how we're going to advance learning.
沒錯，
Yeah,
我看到有一項研究剛剛
I read there was one study that just
最近上了新聞，我還特地坐下來
recently made the news and I actually sat down
我讀完後心裡想
I read it and I was saying
如果你只是複製貼上答案
if you copy paste answers
你根本學不到東西
you don't learn
這讓我覺得很驚訝。
which was just like, wow.
這就像如果我正在訓練
It's like if I were if I were training
準備馬拉松，而你卻說，
for a marathon and you said like,
欸，Leah，
hey, Leah
我可以給你一台滑板車嗎？
can I give you a scooter?
而在某些訓練課程中，
And for some of these training runs
你可能會想騎著滑板車沿著路走。
you'd like take a scooter down the road.
這樣並不會讓我變得更健康。
I wouldn't get into more shape.
這跟剛才那個情況很像。
That was very similar to that.
沒錯。
Yeah.
我覺得令人沮喪的是，
And I think the frustrating thing is like
我認為這裡確實有一些很重要的問題需要討論。
I think there really are important questions to be asked about this.
我確實認為，像批判性思考這樣的能力，
I do think that, you know, critical thinking skills
我們必須思考要怎麼培養這些能力，以及如何持續精進。
we have to think about how we develop these and how we pursue that.
每當我再次看到這種情況時，我都會有點沮喪，
I get a little frustrated that when I see I again
我相信那份研究一定有它合理的解釋，
I'm sure there's a real good defense of that study
但當我看到這類研究時，
but I see studies like this is
你其實只是在陳述一個大家都知道的事實。
you're saying an obvious thing.
我們真正需要思考的是，
The thing we need to think about
我們到底該怎麼實際運用這些工具？
is how do you actually use these tools?
你要如何提升自己的批判性思考能力？
How can you improve your critical thinking skills?
我認為這會是一個開放式的問題。
And I think that's going to be, you know, an open end question.
我們得持續不斷地自我提問。
We're going to have to keep asking ourselves.
你看，我們之所以創建 Study Mood，部分原因是因為
Look, part of the reason why we created Study Mood
它基本上是一種為學生量身打造的輔導體驗，
which is essentially a tutoring experience for students
是為了讓學生不必再學習如何
is so students wouldn't have to learn how to
用特定方式對模型下指令來獲得回饋，
prompt the model in ways that would give feedback
或進行測驗，或推動學習。
or quiz or or drive learning.
相反地，這會是一種你可以進入的模式，
Instead, it would be a mode that you would enter
在這個模式下，模型本身會主動引導你，
where the model itself would push you
並帶領你找到答案，
and would guide you towards answers
同時提供個人化的背景資訊與知識架構。
and personalize and give context and scaffold knowledge.
所以我們正努力在 ChatGPT 中打造這樣的學習體驗，
So we're on this journey to create an experience in chat GPT
讓學生不需要懂得特定的使用方式也能上手。
where a student doesn't have to know how to use it in certain ways.
我認為這就是
And I think that's
你會真正看到
where you're going to really see
學習的界線被不斷推進。
the boundaries of learning being advanced.
是啊，我真的很興奮
Yeah, and I'm I'm excited
因為我聽到一些家長分享的親身經歷
because I'm hearing kind of anecdotal stories
來自家長，他們會
from parents where they'll,
在家長陪同下
while supervised
但會讓孩子開始和ChatGPT對話。
but they'll let their kid start a conversation, the chat GPT.
你很快就會發現ChatGPT
And you quickly realize the chat GPT
對於討論青蛙這件事有無限的耐心。
has infinite patience to talk about frogs.
你永遠不會讓它感到厭煩。
You can never exhaust it.
它可以一直和你聊青蛙。
It'll talk about frogs forever.
而那個剛開始對爬蟲類有興趣的小朋友，可能突然間
And that budding herpetologist might all of a sudden, you know
發現自己真的很喜歡聊這個主題
realize that they really like talking about this
即使他們的父母沒興趣。
even though their parents don't.
ChatGPT神奇的地方之一就是它非常有耐心，
One of the things that's magical about chat GPT is it is patient,
無限地。
infinitely.
所以你問的任何問題
So no question you ask
ChatGPT 永遠不會覺得你的問題愚蠢。
chat GPT is is ever stupid.
它總是會回應你。
It will always respond.
它總是會給你誠實且合理的答案。
It will always give you an honest, reasonable answer.
而且你知道，
And to, you know
學習有一半是在於建立自信和獲得學習的動力。
half of learning is about feeling confident, inspired to learn.
我們在 Coursera 常說的一句話是，
One of the things we always said at Coursera is, you know
打造優秀的課程和技術是一回事，
it's one thing to build amazing courses and amazing tech
但要真正讓孩子學會，
but to really get a kid to learn
你必須讓他們覺得自己學得會，也想要學。
you need to have them feel like I can learn and I want to learn.
我認為我在
I think a lot of what I is doing in the
教育領域做的很多事情，都是在給予
education space is is giving
人們建立信心的支撐
people that scaffolding to have confidence
讓他們能夠勇於投入並學習。
that they can dive in and they can learn.
我之所以來到OpenAI，有一個原因是
So one of the reasons I came to open
其實也和我女兒有關。
I was actually also connected to my daughter.
她有閱讀障礙。
She is she is dyslexic.
而且多年來，
And for years,
我常看到她哥哥下樓，
I would watch her brother come down
早上讀報紙，
in the morning and read the newspaper
我則默默地想，
and I would stick to myself and think, you know
這麼聰明的小女孩，
how is this brilliant little girl going
到底要怎麼學會接觸這個世界？
to actually learn how to access the world?
她要怎麼了解時事呢？
How is she going to learn that about current events?
在我加入OpenAI的前一個夏天，
And the summer before I joined OpenAI
我們推出了進階語音模式。
we launched advanced voice mode.
我記得把手機交給她，跟她說：Zoe，
And I remember handing her the phone and I said, Zoe
你要不要試著跟ChatGPT聊聊看？
why don't you try talking with Chachi Petit?
她說：嘿，ChatGPT
And she said, hey, Chachi Petit
我媽媽擔心我沒辦法了解最新時事
my mom is worried that I'm not going to learn about current events
因為我不像我哥哥那樣能讀報紙。
because I can't read the newspaper like my brother.
你可以跟我說說世界上正在發生什麼事嗎？
Can you tell me what's going on in the world?
那一刻真的很觸動人心，
And it was so poignant as
我記得 ChatGPT 回覆說，
I remember Chachi Petit responding and saying,
當然可以，Zoe，
you know, sure, Zoe
你對哪些事情有興趣？
what are you interested in?
你今天想多了解世界上的哪些事？
What do you want to learn about in the world today?
然後，
And from there,
對話就這樣繼續下去，他們聊起了
the conversation went on and they were talking
她對太空和機器人等各種興趣。
about all her interests in space and robots.
就在那一刻我意識到，
And I realized in that moment that, you know
ChatGPT 將會為這個女孩打開世界的大門。
Chachi Petit was going to unlock the world for this girl.
而我也不用再像以前那樣擔心了。
And I was not going to have to be worried in the same way.
這真的很有力量。
That's powerful.
我很期待看到它如何協助解決這類問題，
I'm excited to see how it helps with issues like that,
像是可近性相關的問題。
accessibility issues.
我覺得未來觀察它的發展會很有趣，
And I think that's it's going to be interesting to see
幾年後我們會走到哪一步。
where we are a few years from now.
Leah，非常感謝你和我聊這些。
Leah, thank you so much for talking with me.
這次對談真的很有意思。
This has been very interesting.
我很期待接下來的發展會如何。
I'm excited to see where these things go next.
太棒了！
Awesome.
很高興和你聊天，Andrew。
Great talking to you, Andrew.
我也想多認識你們兩位一點。
I'd also like to know a little bit more about you both, too.
Yabi，你可以跟我說說你現在在念什麼嗎？
So Yabi, could you tell me what you're studying right now?
嗯，
Yeah.
其實我剛完成了
So I actually just finished up
在南加大修完了傳播學的學士學位，
my undergraduate degree in communication at USC
接下來我要開始第一學期，
and then I'm going to enter the first semester
這是我商業分析碩士課程的一部分，
of my master's program in business analytics,
同樣是在南加州大學。
also at USC.
好啊，聽起來不錯。
OK, cool.
那你為什麼會想選這個呢？
So why did you want to choose that?
剛進大學的時候，
Initially, when I came to college
我其實沒有很確定。
I wasn't really sure.
也不太確定自己想讀什麼科目。
Kind of like the subject matter I wanted to study.
所以我花了很多時間修通識課程來探索。
So I took like a lot of time to take GE courses to kind of explore.
然後在這個過程中，
And then through there
我發現我比較喜歡
I think I like the more of
研究和理論中比較偏向人的那一面。
the human component of like research and theory.
我發現傳播學是一個很
And I found that communication was like a really
適合探索這方面的主修。
good major to like kind of explore that through.
然後在整個大學期間，
And then throughout, like, you know, my college career
我開始修了很多統計課。
I started taking a lot of stat classes
然後，你知道嗎
and then, you know
讓我打下了分析思考的基礎。
gave me the basis for like analytical thinking.
而我真的很想把這部分補上。
And I really wanted to kind of add that on.
所以我又選修了資料科學作為副修，
So I added a data science minor
然後就有了那種
and then kind of having that
創意和分析兩種元素結合在一起的感覺。
like creative and analytical component come together.
我想這也讓我走向了商業分析這條路。
I think it led me to business analytics.
所以這真的是個很有趣的組合。
So that's it's a very interesting combination there.
事情會這樣發展真的很酷。
That's pretty cool the way that came about.
那 Alop，跟我們說說你現在在學什麼吧。
So Alop, tell us what you're studying.
嗯，
Yeah,
我現在在柏克萊大學主修電機工程和電腦科學。
I'm studying electrical engineering and computer science at Berkeley.
我即將升上大二。
I'm a rising sophomore.
是什麼吸引你投入這些領域的？
What brought you into those fields?
我想從小到大
I think growing up
我是在灣區長大的
I grew up in the Bay Area
所以我從小就接觸到很多科技產品。
so I've been exposed to a lot of tech around me.
我本身也很喜歡動手實作。
And I'm also like a really hands on guy.
我喜歡擺弄電路，或寫寫程式碼。
I like fidgeting with circuits or playing around with code.
我很喜歡替我發現的問題找出解決方法。
And I really like finding solutions to some issues that I see.
我發現我最喜歡的方法之一
And I found that one of my favorite ways
就是透過寫程式和硬體工程來解決。
to do that was through code and through hardware engineering.
所以我覺得這兩者結合起來很棒。
So I thought this would be a good combination of the two.
你小時候也喜歡自己動手做東西嗎？
Did you like to build things when you were younger?
對，真的很喜歡。
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
像是我做過太陽能車。
Like I build like a solar powered car.
當然啦。
Oh, of course.
對，就是做一台小的。
Yeah, just like a small one.
後來我又做了一台大的。
And then I built a big one later.
喔，沒錯，當然。
Oh, yeah, obviously.
對啊，沒錯，
Yeah, but yeah,
只要是我能親眼看到的東西，
just anything I could just like
真的能親自看到並想像出來。
really see just in person and visualize.
所以你們兩位都很有前瞻性。
So you guys are both pretty forward thinking.
你可以跟我分享你第一次對 AI 有重大領悟的時刻是什麼嗎？
Could you tell me what was kind of your first big aha moment with AI?
是指任何類型的 AI 嗎？
Any kind of AI in general?
我記得那時我高三，
I remember I was a junior in high school
那時候大家都在討論，欸，你知道
and and this kind of buzz of, oh, do you know
你有聽過 ChatGPT 嗎？
have you heard of ChachiBT?
這個話題開始流傳起來。
Kind of started going around.
其實在那之前 AI 早就已經存在了。
And that was like that was like obviously AI had existed before.
我以前也看過 ASIMO 機器人。
I had witnessed like the Osimo robot.
不知道你有沒有聽過那個。
I don't know if you've heard of that.
對，就是那種人形機器人。
But yeah, so humanoids.
但真正讓我印象深刻的是看到一個 AI，
But but really like seeing like an AI that
我真正能夠使用並互動的是 ChatGPT。
I could actually use and interact with was ChachiBT.
我們大家都圍在我的電腦旁邊。
And we're all huddling around my computer.
我剛剛在 OpenAI 註冊了一個帳號。
And I just made an account with OpenAI.
我有一份作業是要討論如何
And I had an assignment on how
寫我的《梅岡城故事》心得報告。
to write my to kill a mockingbird essay.
我當時心想
And I was like
如果它真的什麼都能做到的話
if it can if it can really do anything
那就來看看它會怎麼寫。
let's see how it writes.
對啊。
Right.
結果它馬上幫我寫出一篇完整的《梅岡城故事》作文。
And boom, it wrote me a full to kill a mockingbird essay.
我沒有拿去用
I did not use it
但看到這一幕真的很酷。
but it was definitely cool to see.
這真的是讓我印象深刻的一刻。
And just like a moment that I really remember.
對，我想再多問你一些關於這件事的細節。
Yeah, I want to ask you a little bit more about that.
那你呢？
So how about you?
對我來說，我覺得
I think for me
說真的，我覺得這很有趣，因為
it was honestly funny because I think a
很多人一開始都是用在學術上
lot of people started off with like an academic
或是拿來當作學習用途。
or like study use case for it.
但我記得我偶然發現它的時候
But then I think when I stumbled across from it
我記得那時候我是大二生，
I remember I was like a sophomore,
大二的第一學期。
my first semester of sophomore year in college.
我在社群媒體上看到有人分享說，
And I saw like the social media posts about like how, you know
你可以用 ChatGPT 做一些事情，像是
you kind of use ChachiBT for like certain like, you know
幫我寫故事。
write a story for me.
所以我第一次給它的指令就是寫同人小說，
And so I think my first prompt to it was to like write fanfiction
這真的超好笑。
which is like really funny.
這只是個很隨性的用途。
And like it was just like a random use case.
我還記得我拿給室友看，
I remember showing my roommates
說真的，他們都覺得蠻蠢的。
and they all thought it was pretty stupid, honestly.
所以我覺得那時候大多都是一些很平常、隨機的使用情境。
And so I think it was just like a lot of mundane, random use cases.
然後我記得是到後來
And then I think it was like later
我才真的開始在學業上使用它
on that I actually started using it like academically
特別是當我開始修更多偏重程式設計的課程時。
specifically when I started doing like more coding oriented classes.
但我覺得讓我有頓悟的時刻是
But I think that aha moment for me is the fact
你其實可以把它用在日常瑣事上
that you can use it for like day to day tasks
而不只是用在教育研究上。
and less so for like educational research.
我不能就這樣放過這個話題。
I can't let this drop.
你剛剛提到同人小說。
You mentioned fanfiction.
是哪一種同人小說？
What fanfiction?
我先補充一下背景
So just to give context
我覺得我年輕的時候
I feel like when I was younger
就跟大多數人一樣。
as most people do.
這沒有什麼好評價的。
There's no judgment.
你不用特別了解背景。
You don't have to context.
這裡沒有人會評斷你。
There's no judgment here.
謝謝。
Thank you.
這感覺很像 ChatGPT。
This feels like ChachiBT.
但別跟他這麼說。
But don't say that to him.
我懂你的意思。
I see what you're saying.
太棒了。
That's great.
嗯，
But so yeah,
我覺得有很多不同類型的
so I think there's like a lot of different kind
很誇張的同人小說正在流行。
of like outlandish like fanfictions like kind of going on.
我覺得其中一個讓我印象深刻的社群
And I think one of the communities that I thought
就是史瑞克同人小說社群，真的蠻有趣的。
was like pretty funny was like the Shrek fanfiction community.
不好意思。
Sorry.
真的很抱歉。
I'm sorry.
我剛剛以為你說的是史瑞克同人小說社群。
I thought you said the Shrek fanfiction community.
你可以再說一次嗎？
Could you say this again?
沒錯，就是史瑞克同人社群。
Yes, the Shrek fanfiction community.
好，所以你真的有說過那句話。
Okay, so you did say that.
對，
Yeah,
所以我也不太確定為什麼那時會這樣想，
and so I think I don't know why that was like
那就是我腦海中第一個想要引導的套路。
the top of mind kind of trope that I wanted to prompt.
而且那時候真的還很早期。
And back then it was like super early.
所以產出的內容品質也沒那麼好。
So it wasn't like the outputs weren't as good.
沒錯。
Right.
但我覺得這絕對有機會，
But I feel like this could definitely, you know
成為那些大家常常寫同人小說的平台之一。
be on one of those platforms that they write fanfiction all the time.
這很有趣，因為其中一部分原因是，
It's interesting because like part of it is, you know
同人創作的價值之一，就是讓粉絲能夠參與其中，
part of the value of fanfiction is it's a way for fans to participate
而且他們可以創作出很酷的東西，
and they can produce something that's cool
這些東西可能會吸引你，然後
that can kind of appeal to you and
你拿給朋友看，他們會一臉驚訝地說：什麼？
you showed your friends and they were like, what?
他們會覺得，這很蠢。
They're like, this is stupid.
但對你來說，這卻成就了一個很棒的時刻。
But for you, it created a neat moment.
我覺得這是我們很常忽略的事情。
I think that's a lot of things we forget.
像我自己會寫作，而且我很熱愛寫作。
Like I write and I love to write.
對我來說，寫作的體驗本身就是重點。
Part of the writing experience for me though is the writing.
有人會說，喔，
I have people like, oh
你在Open Air工作過。
you worked at Open Air.
你可以直接用ChatGPT就好啦。
You can just chat GPT.
這就像是在問某人，
It's like that's like asking somebody
為什麼要學彈電吉他，
to learn to play the electric guitar
還是你只是想一直聽電吉他音樂，
or are you just going to have, you know,
而不是真的去彈電吉他，
play electric guitar music all the
而不是親自去彈吉他？
time instead of actually playing the guitar?
不是啊，我學寫作就是為了親自去創作、去做這些事情。
Like no, I learned to write to write to do these things.
我覺得這一點常常被忽略。
I think that kind of gets overlooked
但在那個時候，你就可以說：欸，那這種情況怎麼辦？
but that where you can say, hey, what about this scenario?
而《史瑞克》的同人小說大概是最單純又可愛的東西了。
And Shrek fanfiction is like the most sweet and innocent thing.
我想我可能有聽過。
I think I possibly could have heard.
那你覺得你的教授們是怎麼調適的？
So how would you say your professors have been adapting?
我覺得就實際作業來說，
I think in terms of like actual assignments work
我覺得我現在的感受
I feel like the way I'm feeling about
跟我以前的感覺很像，
it is like similar to like how I felt
就像我們小學時期那樣，
when like when we were younger in like elementary school
我們正在經歷從
we're transitioning between like doing
手算除法轉換到使用
like hand division to like using
計算機來處理更複雜的題目，
calculators to like take on like bigger tasks,
就像你說的那樣。
like you said.
所以我覺得現在就是那種過渡期，
So I feel like it's like that kind of transitional period
我覺得很多時候，
where it's like I think a lot of
自動化的任務變得比較少了。
a lot less like like automation like automotive tasks.
我覺得在我的溝通課程裡
So like I feel like in my communication courses
我發現像是那種定義式的問題變少了
like I'm seeing a lot less like at like as
這種針對術語下定義的問題越來越少，反而更多是
defined this like term kind of question and more about like
要怎麼實際應用這個術語？
how do you apply this term?
這個在更大的脈絡下代表什麼意思？
What does this mean in like a bigger context?
所以我覺得課程更強調意義
So I feel like there's a lot more focus on like meaning
還有背後的意圖，而不是
and like intentionality as opposed to
只是基本的理解而已
kind of more like basic understanding.
而且我覺得，你知道的
And I think, you know
很多考試的形式其實
a lot of tests taking forms are actually like
比我原本想像的還要開放
more open format than I thought they would be.
也因為這樣
And because of that
題目的方向也變成更常問那種，你知道的
the questions have also shifted to ask more of like, you know
可以延伸到更大意義的問題
questions that are like, you know,
而不是只停留在表面的理解
could be extrapolated to like bigger meanings as opposed
就像是那種典型的「請定義這個詞」的題目。
to kind of like the typical like define this term.
所以我覺得這就是我觀察到的改變。
So I feel like that's how I've seen a change.
對，我其實有注意到在我的資工課程裡，有些教授
Yeah, I've actually noticed that in in my CS classes, some professors
很明顯他們不希望我們使用
obviously they want us to not use
AI 來完成這些簡單的作業
it for these like simple homework assignments
這些作業只是用來檢查
that are just like check for check
你是否真的記得那些概念。
to see if you actually remember the concept.
但對於比較大型的專案
But for bigger projects
我們其實有兩種選擇。
we actually got two tracks.
一種是可以用 AI 的
We could take one is with using AI
另一種則是不用 AI 的
and one is without using AI
而且
and
我覺得教授願意這樣做真的很有趣，因為他算是
I thought it was really interesting that the professor is kind of
接受這個新概念並且去適應它。
you this this new concept and and adapting to it.
而且教授說如果用 AI 的話
And the professor said with AI
我們要給你一個稍微更有挑戰性的作業
we're going to give you a bit of a harder assignment
而且我們會再多給你一點壓力
and we're going to push you more
你還需要寫一篇心得，說說 AI 帶給你的啟發
and you're going to have to write a reflection on what AI gave you so
這樣你也能掌握 AI 想傳達給你的概念
that you also get the concepts that you would that AI would tell you.
但如果不用 AI，你就會做比較傳統的專案
But with the non AI you would kind of do a more traditional project
但如果用 AI，你可以把專案做得更深入、更有突破
but with AI you could like push it much further.
所以這真的很棒
So it was great to
教授讓你們可以在這兩種方式中選擇
that the professor was allowing you to choose between the two.
你最後選了哪一個？
Which did you choose?
我選了不用 AI 的那個
I chose non AI.
好，嗯，對啊
Okay, but um, yeah
我知道很多人都選了用 AI 的那個
I know a lot of people who did choose AI.
你為什麼會選不用 AI 的？
Why did you choose non AI?
我覺得對我來說
I think that for me
我本身不是那種技術很強的人
I I wasn't the I wasn't the most like technically
像是與產品概念相契合的聲音
like sound with the concept that the product was about
我記得我自己有幾個想加入的功能
and I remember that I had a few features that I
自己想在這種小遊戲裡實現
myself wanted to implement in this in this kind of mini game
但有了 AI，你可以請它幫你發想點子
but with AI it was like you can ask it to brainstorm
還能協助你產生功能想法
and help you get features
你也可以用 AI 來實現這些功能
and you can implement those with AI
但我其實已經知道自己想做什麼
but I kind of knew what I wanted to do
一開始就已經有自己的想法了
from the get-go and because I already had my ideas.
我很常用 AI 來發想點子
I use AI a lot for brainstorming
但因為我早就有想法了，所以我就覺得
but because I already had my ideas I was like
那我乾脆專注
oh I might as well just really just like focus
在實現我已經想到的點子上
on implementing the ideas that I had already come up with.
這種情況很常見
That's a it's a thing
經常會遇到，因為我覺得有些
comes up a lot because I think some
有些教授希望學生學好基礎知識
professors they want the students to learn the fundamentals
這很重要，因為如果你學會了 Python，
which is important because if you learn Python
你真的需要學會 Python。
you really need to learn Python
我認為這在未來幾十年都會很有幫助。
and I think it's going to be helpful for even for decades to come.
我們需要有懂得這些運作原理的人。
We need to have people who understand how these things work
但我有看過一些課程，
but I've seen some programs
他們甚至沒有教學生如何
where they're not even teaching them how
利用 AI 來產生程式碼，
to use AI for like code generation
在我看來，這根本就是教學失職，你懂吧？
which to me sounds like malpractice, you know
當然，這只是我個人的看法。
which again just that's my take on that.
但我覺得這個想法很不錯，
But I think that I like the idea
就是有不同的課程可以選擇，
that there's a different courses
還有如果你打算使用
and the idea that if you're going to use
AI，那很好，你就必須接受更大的挑戰。
AI then great you have to do bigger challenges
也有人問過我這個問題。
and I've had people ask me about this.
如果大家都能用 ChatGPT，那我們該怎麼辦？
What do we do people can use chat GPT?
我會讓學生做更大型的專題計畫
I'm like have students do bigger projects
你知道，以前他們只會做讀書報告
you know where they would have done a book report
現在我會讓他們拍攝音樂影片，
before have I make a music video,
就是讓他們做更有規模的作品，做更多不同的嘗試。
you know, just make bigger things and do more.
我覺得這些擔憂是有道理的
I think they're valid concerns
當大家面對某些事物時，
when people are looking at something that's
這些事物會改變我們的工作方式，
going to change the way that we work
大家都在試著了解最後會有什麼結果。
and trying to figure out the outcome.
所以我能理解大家的猶豫，
And so I understand some of the hesitation there
我也認為批判性思考能力非常重要，
and I do think that critical thinking skills are important
我覺得這項技術也正努力去配合這一點，
and I think this technology is trying to adapt to that
因為如果它只是另一種
because if it's just another thing that
讓大家只會複製貼上的工具，
people copy paste from them like yeah
那其實學不到東西。
you're not going to learn.
所以要睜大眼睛，關注新功能，深入研究 ChatGPT。
So opening eyes rolling out a new feature study the chat GPT
這似乎是一種非常有趣的做法。
which seems to be kind of very interesting approach with that.
你們有試過這個嗎？
Have you guys tried this?
那你們會怎麼形容它？
Yeah, what's your how would you describe it?
我會說學習模式其實就是一種對話。
I would say that study mode is is a chat.
它很有挑戰性，會讓使用者
It's challenging and it forces forces the user
真的去挑戰自己對各種內容的理解。
to actually challenge themselves with any sort of content.
像我自己在嘗試時，
So I myself when I tried it
我請它教我人工智慧相關的知識，
I I asked it to teach me about AI
我也用一般聊天模式試過，
and I also tried this with a regular chat mode
它只是給我一大堆關於人工智慧的清單，
and it just gave me a big list of oh AI
說有這種學習方式、那種學習方式，
is this there's this type of learning this type of learning
但當我用學習模式時，
and when I asked study mode.
它其實沒有直接回答我的問題，
It actually just didn't even answer my question
反而丟給我三個問題，想了解我真正想要的是什麼，
and gave me three questions to understand what I really wanted
還問我有沒有特定想了解的主題？
and it said do you have a specific topic that you
我真的很想深入了解你對這個有多少認識？
really want to get into how much do you know about this?
你現在正在做什麼？
What are you doing right now?
然後我把話題聚焦到一個特定主題，
And I got it to a specific topic which is
就是微調，它真的一項一項地詳細說明，
fine-tuning and it really broke it down one by one
我覺得學習模式最重要的一點是，
and I think the biggest thing about study mode is
它不會只是單純假設，
that it doesn't just assume
你已經記住了，然後幾分鐘後就跳過。
that you remember it and move on maybe after a few minutes.
它會回頭提醒你，喔，
It'll go back and say, oh
這裡有個小小的自我檢查，確認一下你是否理解。
here's a little mental check a little sanity check.